本节我们的目标是构建安全压缩函数
So our goal for this segment is to build
secure compression functions. So
使得压缩函数是抗碰撞的。提醒一下
compression functions are collision
resistant. So just to remind you where we
我们看Merkle-Damgard机制里
are we looked at this Merkle Damgard
construction which takes a little
用到了一个小压缩函数，根据它构建了一个哈希函数
compression function and builds from it a
hash function for much, much larger
来处理长得多的输入。我们证明了这个可爱的定理，
事实上，如果一个小压缩函数h是抗碰撞的
inputs. We proved this cute theorem that
in fact if a little compression function h
那么把这个h带入Merkle-Damgard机制里
is collision resistant then plugging in
into the Merkle Damgard construction
会给我们一个抗碰撞的哈希函数，来处理更长的输入
gives us a collision resistant hash
function for larger inputs. So now in this
本节我们的目标是构建一个抗碰撞的压缩函数
segment our goal is basically to build a
compression function that is collision
我们将看到一组机制
resistant. So we're going to see a couple
of constructions. And so the first
我们想到的第一个问题是，我们能否从已有的原型
question that comes to mind is well, can
we build compression functions from
来构造压缩函数呢？特别地，我们花了大量工夫
primitives that we already have? In
particular, we spent a lot of work to
来构建分组密码，问题是，我们能否从
分组密码来构建压缩函数？
build block cyphers and the question is
can we build compression functions from
答案是肯定的，我来告诉大家怎么办
block cyphers. And the answer is yes. And
let me show you how to do it. So assume we
假设我们这里有一个特定的分组密码，用来处理N位分组
have a certain block cypher here that
operates on N bits blocks, so the input is
那么输入是N位，输出也是N位。有一个经典的机制
an N bits, output is N bits. And then
there's this classic construction called a
叫做Davies-Meyer机制，我用符号的形式写在这了
Davies-Meyer construction which I wrote
down in symbols here. Basically says that
给定信息分组和链接变量
what you would do is, given the message
block and the chaining variable, all we do
我们使用信息分组作为密钥，来加密链接变量
is we encrypt the chaining variable using
the message block as the key. And then we
然后我们在输出上再做一次异或。那么
这可能看起来有点奇怪
kind of do one more xor on the output. So
this might seem a little bizarre, because
因为记得信息分组完全是在攻击者的控制之下
remember the message block is something
that's completely under the control of the
攻击者试图找到碰撞，这样他可以选择
他想要的信息分组
adversary. He's trying to find the
collision so he can choose the message
我们把这个信息分组作为一个分组密码的密钥
blocks however he wants. And yet we're
using this message block as a key into a
不过，我们可以证明这个机制
block cypher. But nevertheless, we can
argue that this construction, at least
至少当E是一个理想的密码时，我们可以证明
when E is what's called an ideal cypher,
we can argue that this construction is in
这个机制事实上是抗碰撞的。让我们看这个定理
fact as collision resistant as possible.
So let me state the theorem. The theorem
这个定理是说，如果E是一个理想的分组密码
states that, as I said, if E is an ideal
block cypher, meaning that it's a random
意味着它是一个｛0,1｝^N上的随机置换的集合，
如何置换由密钥K确定
collection of K random permutations from
｛0,1｝ to the N to 01 to the N. Then under
然后在这个E是理想的分组密码的假设下，
事实上，找到这个压缩函数H的碰撞
that assumption that E's an ideal block
cypher, in fact, finding the collision for
需要2的N/2次方的时间。特别地
this compression function H takes time,
two to the N over two. In particular, we
我们可以证明，任何能找到碰撞的人必须
can show that anyone who is finding
collisions has to evaluate the encryption
至少花掉2的N/2次方的时间来加、解密
and decryption functions at least 2 to
the N over 2 times. And if you think
这意味着，因为这个压缩函数只有N位长
about what that means, since the output of
this compression function is only N bits
我们知道总有一个通用的生日攻击
long, we know that there's always a
generic birthday attack that finds
可以在2的N/2次方的时间里找到碰撞。
所以这个定理是说
collisions in time 2 to the N over 2.
So basically this theorem says that this
这个抗碰撞函数确是抗碰撞的
collision resistant function is as
collision resistant as possible. We can
我们可以在2的N/2次方的时间里找到碰撞，
通过使用生日攻击的方式
find the collision in time 2 to the N
over 2 using the birthday attack but
但没有算法可以做得比2的N/2次方更好
there is no algorithm that will do better
than 2 to the n over 2. So this
这是一个在抗碰撞哈希中很常见的压缩函数
is actually a very common compression
function used in collision resistance
事实上SHA函数都使用了Davies-Mayer机制
hashing in fact of a SHA
functions all used Davies-Mayer. It turns
实际上Davies-Mayer机制有些特别的地方
out that there is something special about
the Davies-Mayer construction that
使得该机制是抗碰撞的。如果仅仅是猜这个机制
makes collision resistant. If you just try
to guess the construction very likely you
很有可能最终得到的不是抗碰撞的压缩函数
will end up with something that is not
collision resistant. And so let me ask you
我问大家下面这个问题。假设我们如下定义了压缩函数
the following puzzle. Suppose we actually
define the compression function as
我们加密这个链接变量H，使用目前分组作为密钥
follows, namely all we do is we encrypt
the chaining variable H using the current
不同之处在于，我们不做Davies-Mayer机制里的
message block as the key. So the
difference is that we dropped this 'xor' H
这一步异或。我们干脆忽略它。当它不存在
in Davies-Mayer, we simply ignored it. So
it's not there. And the puzzle for you
给大家的问题是，求证这个压缩函数不是抗碰撞的
is show me that this compression function
then is actually not collision resistant.
我们看，我们试图构建一个碰撞，即一对不同的
So, let's see, so we're trying to build a
collision, namely a distinct pair of HM
M和M'能在这个函数H下发生碰撞
and H' M' that happen to collide
under this later function H. And my
我的问题是怎么构造这个碰撞？我将告诉大家
question to you is how would you do it? So
I'm already going to tell you that you're
选择任意的H,M和M'。唯一的要求是
going to choose H, M, and M'
arbitrarily. The only requirement is that
M与M'不同。然后我的问题是，如何构建H'
M and M' are distinct. And then my
question is, how would you construct an H'
可以找出碰撞？答案是，我们首先选择
that would cause a collision to pop
out? So the answer is the first choice and
一个简单的方法来解释之。如果我们使用加密函数
an easy way to see it is if we apply the
encryption function using M' to both
对两边进行加密，以M'为密钥。然后我们得到了
H'用E和密钥M'加密的结果
sides. Then we get that this is basically
E of M' applied to H', right.
这是我们以M'为密钥通过加密左边获得的
this is what we get by applying encryption
using M' to the left hand side. And
如果我们以M'为密钥，加密右边
if we apply encryption using M' to
the right hand side, the decryption
解密操作会被抵消，只剩下M的加密结果
operator cancels out and we simply are
left with the encryption of M, H, which is
即为我们想找的碰撞。大家可以看到
exactly the collision that we wanted to
find. So there. You can see that it's
这里使用了解密函数D，容易为压缩函数构建碰撞
basically by using the decryption function
D, it's very easy to build collisions for
现在我应该告诉大家，事实上Davies-Meyer
this compression function. Now I should
tell you that in fact Davies-Meyer is not
不是唯一的。还有其他方法可以根据分组密码，
构建抗碰撞的压缩函数
unique. There are other ways to build
collision resistant compression functions
例如，有Miyaguchi-Preneel方法
from block ciphers. For example, here's a
method called Miyaguchi Preneel. Miyaguchi
Miyaguchi-Preneel方法在WHIRLPOOL哈希函数中
有所使用，我们之前也是看到过WHIRLPOOL
Preneel actually is used in WHIRLPOOL hash
function that we saw earlier. Here is
这是另一种方法，可以得到一个抗碰撞的压缩函数
another method that happens to result in a
collision resistant compression function.
有12种变体，就像这样玩弄各种异或
And there are twelve variants like this
playing with XORs and placing the
以及把变量放在不同位置等手段，都可以
得到一个抗碰撞的机制
variables in different slots that will
actually give a collision resistant
但也有许多类似的变体，就像我们在上一问题里
mechanism. But there are also many, many
variants of this like we saw in the
所看到的，并不是抗碰撞的。这是另一个例子
previous puzzle that are not collision
resistant. So here's. Another example,
它不是抗碰撞的。我将把它留为家庭作业
that's not collision resistant. And I'm
gonna leave it as a homework problem to
来解出这个机制的一个碰撞
figure out a collision for this
construction. So now, basically, we have
现在，对于描述SHA-256哈希函数来说，我们万事俱备了
all the ingredients to describe the
SHA-256 hash function. I'll tell
我会告诉大家，SHA-256是Merkel-Damgard机制
you that it's a Merkel-Damgard
construction, exactly as the one that we
我们之前看过Merkel-Damgard机制。SHA-256
还使用了Davies-Mayer压缩函数
saw before. It uses a Davies-Mayer
compression function. And so the only
唯一的问题是，Davies-Mayer的底层分组密码是什么？
question is, what's the underlying block
cipher for Davies-Mayer? And that block
这个分组密码叫做SHACAL-2。我会告诉大家它的参数
cipher is called SHACAL-2. And I'll
just tell you its parameters. It uses a
它使用了512位密钥。记得密钥是从信息分组里提取的
512 bit key. And remember the key is taken
from the message block. So, this is really
这是信息分组。它刚好是512位
what the message block is. And it so
happens to be 512 bits. Which means the
意味着SHA-256一次会处理它的512位输入信息
SHA-256 will process its input
message 512 bits at a time. And in the
这个分组密码的分组大小是256位。
然后这些是链接变量
block size, for this block cipher is
256 bits. And these are the chaining variable.
这是H_i-1。这应该是连续的链接变量
So this would be H i-1.
And this would be successive chaining variable.
现在大家有了对SHA-256工作的完整理解
So now you have a complete
understanding of how SHA-256 works.
我这里不描述SHACAL-2密码的内容
Module of this cipher SHACAL-2 I'm not going to describe here.
如我所说，一类压缩函数是由分组密码构建
So as I said, one class of compression functions is built from block cyphers. It turns out there's another class of
还有一类压缩函数是由数论里的困难问题构建的
compression functions that's built using
hard problems from number theory, and I
我想非常简要地给大家一个例子。
我们说这些压缩函数是可证实的
want to very briefly show you one example.
And we call these compression functions
因为如果你可以找到这种压缩函数的碰撞
provable because if you can find the
collision on this compression function
那么你就可以解决非常困难的理论问题
then you're going to be able to solve a
very hard number theoretic problem which
一般这类问题是难解的。因此，如果数论问题是难解的
is believed to be intractable. And as a
result, if the number theory problem is
得到的压缩函数可被证实是抗碰撞的
intractable, the resulting compression
function is provably a collision
这是这个压缩函数的工作过程
resistant. So here's how this compression
function works. Basically we're going to
我们选取一个大质数，这是一个非常大的质数，
约700个十进制数，2000位二进制数
choose a large prime piece, so this is a
gigantic prime, something like 700 digits,
我们选择两个随机数U和V
2,000 bits. And then we're going to
choose two random values, U and V, between
在1到P之间。现在如下定义压缩函数
one and P. And now let's define the
compression function as follows. It takes
它在0和P-1之间取两个数，输出0和P-1之间的一个数
two numbers between 0, and p-1,
and it's gonna output one number between
那么其压缩率为2比1
0, and  p-1. So it's compression
ratio is 2 to 1. And takes two
取两个数，输出一个数。在从0到P-1的范围里
numbers. And outputs one number. In the
range 0 to p-1.
然后计算双重指数，计算U的H次方乘以V的N次方
And it does it basically by computing double exponentiation. It
computes u to the H times v to the n.
现在这个定理表述为一个事实
And the theorem, which, right now, I'm just
gonna state as a fact. This fact actually
事实上，这是很直接就能证明的。我们以后再看
turns out to be fairly straightforward to
prove, and we're gonna do it later on when
当我们讲到本课程的数论部分时再说
we get to the number theoretic part of the
course. The fact is, that if you can find
事实上，如果你可以找到这个压缩函数的一个碰撞，
那么你就可以解一个标准的数论难题
a collision for this compression function,
then you can solve a standard hard
叫做离散对数问题。所有人都相信
problem in number theory called a discreet
log problem. Everyone believes discrete
离散对数问题是困难的，因此这个压缩函数
log is hard, and as a result, this
compression function is provably collision
可证实是抗碰撞的。那么大家可能会问，
为什么在实际中，人们不使用这种压缩函数呢？
resistant. So you might ask me why do
people not use this compression function
为什么SHA-256不用它？
in practice. Why would we not use this for
SHA-256? And the answer is that this
答案是与分组密码相比，这个压缩函数速度太慢了
gives very slow performance in comparison
to what you get from a block cipher. So
所以它在实际的压缩函数中不被使用
this is not really used for any
compression functions. However, if for
但是，如果出于某些原因，你就是想用它
来算MAC或签名，对于一段长信息
some reason you really only want to, say,
MAC or sign. Just one long message, and
你需要花上一天时间来完成计算，然后
当然你也可以使用它的
you have a whole day to do it, then
certainly you can use this type of
虽然它很慢，但你可以获得可证实是抗碰撞的函数
compression function. And even though it's
slow, you'll get something that's provably
本节完结，现在我们准备讨论HMAC了
collision resistant. Okay, so that's the
end of this segment. And now we're finally
下节开始讲HMAC
ready to talk about HMAC, which we're
gonna do in the next segments.